[SPEAKER_00]: Prate, can you explain the practice of samatha and vipassana?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, we can start by sort of applying a blanket.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or maybe I just, I will start with some idea which I took yesterday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, yeah, you can do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it was after, you know, talking with you about
[SPEAKER_00]: This phenomenological approach, seeing the peripheral, I was still considering that actually to practice just simple ānāpāna meditation as I used to do it, you know, just relax, staying in the present with your breathing, is actually still a good thing to do in your spare time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it seems that you have something to say about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I think one... what did I say yesterday?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, basically, most... more often than not, it won't be a good thing, because you won't do it mindfully.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you... if you... if you go onto an object of meditation, whatever that might be, and if you want to do it just to sort of
[SPEAKER_01]: Calm down and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can do it, but on the basis of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the basis of mindfulness, as we've been discussing all these previous talks, is the basis of the awareness of the peripheral.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said yesterday, sure, you can't possibly sustain, although you could surprise yourself, but the amount of energy you can invest in sort of repetition of this discernment of the peripheral in regard to actual and actual in regard to peripheral,
[SPEAKER_01]: So that you fully, sort of, keep drilling that in, training and drilling, training and drilling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but say you're tired of it, so then, yes, you stop actively pursuing the discernment of that principle, but you don't then turn completely away and then remain and become unmindful, become unaware of the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that means you're not mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means when you go to meditate, if you meditate without being aware of the principle,
[SPEAKER_01]: You meditate without mindfulness, which means that's not meditation at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it can be still a wholesome activity.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you are not engaged in sensual desires, you're doing something unwholesome... Well, it's wholesome in a very relative manner, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's wholesome because... only because you don't engage in sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it remains very much unwholesome, because it won't take you out of the putujana status, nor will it take you out of the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the contrary, it will probably keep perpetuating the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said those meditators, samanas and brāhmaṇas, without the right view, they end up meditating... they think they meditate, but they end up premeditating, overmeditating, mismeditating, undermeditating, and all those kind of permutations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because why?
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is still bound with sensuality, with the notions of self, with all the wrong assumptions, and they meditate with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a patujana cannot meditate with a pure mind, because he doesn't have such a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't even have a concept of what phenomena the mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he can purify his mind by practicing jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And jhānas are nothing other than fully established upon the principle of mindfulness, which is the principle we've been discussing, which I think maybe was even recorded.
[SPEAKER_01]: I explained to you that extending the same awareness of the peripheral in regard to... you can go as far as to the kasiṇas, the four great elements, the element of consciousness, which is the most refined one, to all the jhānas, to the immaterial mental establishments.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the extending the mind along the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Sariputin, one by one, that's the Thirumajivinikāya, goes to the first jhāna, and then he kind of, ah, recognizes the factors that are there, and says this is all kind of being held by mindfulness, and then he's there beyond, and then following the same principles, he says, yeah, there is beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then he goes higher, higher, higher, higher, higher, until, obviously, with his right view, he reaches to the cessation of perception and feeling, which is obviously that there is no beyond that
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's just to see how far this this great structure kind of stretches itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there beyond this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Up to the infinite space, the infinite consciousness, neither perception or no perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: All those things in regard to mind being developed in regard to that peripheral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you... when you're able to sort of reach... and it's not like it's abstract now, because the mind is not developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for the developed mind, reaching the... the verges of the phenomenon of space, goes into the infinite space.
[SPEAKER_01]: The verges of the... surmounting the perceptions of unity and diversity, doesn't matter a particular general nature of perception surmounted, you reach a base of neither perception or no perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So jhānas, that's why the Buddha praised the jhānas, because even... Sure, you don't need necessarily the right view, but in order to do them, you're doing them along the right view, along the right principle, along the principles of pratītyānupāda, along the principles of surmounting sensuality, surmounting the master I am of the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many, so to say, that I am cannot be present in the jhānas, it ceases beforehand, that's why the man enters jhānas and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why they would appraise them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were to develop jhānas as patrūjanas, then you would need very, very little instruction to to put it all together and become probably an arahant right away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind is already developed to such an extent that it has surmounted the domain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: has fully understood the nature of saḷāyātana, and its impermanence, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's very important to recognize that Putujana cannot meditate rightly, unless he's a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's a strong statement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, that's... Well, you don't need to go further than Samādhīti sutta and see that right view makes everything right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not my statement, it's the whole sutta about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you meditate rightly if you have no right view?
[SPEAKER_01]: And the story?
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... it can be done without you knowing that you are meditating rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just meditate and prepare your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you don't know it... Well, if right view is about the knowledge, if liberation is about the knowledge, how can you be knowing while not knowing?
[SPEAKER_01]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: how can you be doing it rightly while not knowing?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not knowing... Well, the one who understands those instructions is the Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody shorter than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you follow something you haven't understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you follow it?
[SPEAKER_01]: If I give you instruction, and you make no sense out of it, how can you perform it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you just follow instructions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You give me some task to do, and I don't understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you won't do the task rightly, if the task is based upon you understanding the task.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the Buddha didn't say just perform these mechanical things and you'll get to the final result.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, understand what I'm teaching you and then you will be your own kind of leader, your own sort of guide to the final task.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you're sort of talking about would be as if the Buddha gave this impersonal sort of set of methods and instructions that you can just stick to it and you will arrive at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he didn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: He did give instructions that need to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, the right view comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said himself, nirvāṇa-dhīti-sutta, why is saṃsamādhi right?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because of the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, without the right view, you cannot meditate rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but, but on the other hand, I'm not saying but, but, but... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But on the other hand, we have quite a few examples of people who have jhānas and they're still put to jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, theoretically, as puthujjana, you can develop jhānas, you can develop the full understanding of this principle and develop your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not necessarily, until somebody tells you externally, turn that to the nature of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why puthujjana can be free from all the other upādānas except the upādāna of the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a sutta, Bhāgavata, I think it's in Majjhima Nikaya, or maybe in Uttara, not sure, where putujan can be free from sensuality, can be free from sūla-bhāta-paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: He cannot be free from the self-view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because for that, you need utterance of another.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he will have very much of ayoniso manasikāra if he had jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, like you say jhānas, the four jhānas, but then you have even kind of more refined immaterial attainments.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why when the Buddha became the Buddha, when the Brahma pleaded to him to go and teach,
[SPEAKER_01]: Who should I teach?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're all kutujanas, but which ones have the least dust in their eyes?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he turned to his previous teacher, not out of some traditional gratitude or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because he had the least dust in his eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was the basis of neither perception nor perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, as a kutujana, he was really, really... he'd done 99.9% of work that arahant needs to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: All he needed is just that one, 0.1%, to set everything rightly, that he already had.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when they told him, the Devas told him, he died, he said, why?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a really great loss for him.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, unimaginable loss, because he actually was so, so close to this very thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, he went down the next one, which is the base of, uh, infinite space, whatever it was, all for the purpose, because they had, they'd done all the work, mostly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why when you do have people in the sūtras, they heard just one line from the Buddha and became arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because they've done all the work rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they developed the whole understanding that resulted in the whole freedom of upādāna and everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just needed that last drop.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they did a lot of samarāyaṭa understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Really?
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if Buddha comes to you and tells you, in seeing, let there be the seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: In heard, let there only be the heard.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you understand that right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be able to understand that if you have many wrong views blocking it, covering it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you clear all the wrong views, but you're not still quite there yet, and then somebody tells you that, and you understand it as clear as a day, as they tell to you, you can only do that if the mind is able to to sort of reach it at that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it can reach that level if it made the right effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, again,
[SPEAKER_01]: You should keep trying to meditate and keep trying to sort of understand along the lines of understanding, not along the lines of mechanical technique, which you hope is purifying your mind somewhere down the line.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even if it were, you have no right criteria, you don't have right view to recognize what the actual purity is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if it sits on your face, you won't recognize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I, I, it seems that I can agree with this statement, that last one you said,
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I will show you my understanding, which I used to, for which I have.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was thinking that you purify your mind from nirvana.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by purifying your mind from nirvana, you remove the obstacles, and then you can create.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sure, that's not wrong statement to make, but purifying your mind of nirvana is done by understanding what nirvana are.
[SPEAKER_01]: By full understanding the nature, you surmount it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Mahārāja Moggallānā entered the first jhāna, by understanding what the first jhāna was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by doing this or that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can we say that actually overcoming... you overcome nivārāṇa by understanding what nivārāṇa is, means that you don't overcome them by technique, by just practicing some meditation?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you overcome by understanding that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how the mind develops in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And understanding can take place only on the basis of principle of tatticamāpāda, the basic principle of understanding that a reason phenomenon as it has a reason, which means on the basis of mindfulness, which means on the basis of discerning peripheral in regard to the actual or actual in regard to peripheral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because nivāraṇas are also phenomena that are manifested in your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you understand it there, on the basis of the experience as a whole, you remove the ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remain... you remove, sort of, their influence over you, by not owning them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you give them power by taking possession of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what about, eh... eh... sotāpāna, and then sakadāgāmī, anagāmī, they still have...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, to an extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: To an extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said before, even with this principle that you can kind of understand, you still didn't fully understand it, didn't you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you haven't repeated it long enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why an ārya, who is still not an ārahant, still has work to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: He still needs to keep re-engaging in repeating of the same principle, of the same understanding that he has, which is why nobody else can be his guide.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: He himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: He got a criteria, he got a principle, he got a base for it, he got an understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: He just needs to keep drilling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just Buddha at first?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just keep drilling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha Vipassi, before he became Samasambuddha,
[SPEAKER_01]: He discerned paticca-sampada.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in that, and in Kāyā-sutta, he describes paticca-sampada, and he comes to the point of nāmarūpa determines viññāṇa, and viññāṇa determines nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he doesn't define paticca-sampada further.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he says, by understanding that, he remained contemplating manifestation arising and ceasing of the five aggregates, of the experience as a whole, until his mind was purified from all of the, all of the kilesas, and he became sama-sambuddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if he understood the principle, then just remain drilling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it doesn't say he remained drilling Pāṭhita-saṃpāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says he understood Pāṭhita-saṃpāda, nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, viññāṇa, nāmarūpa, and then he remained just being mindful of arising and falling of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of the enduring of the five aggregates, of persisting, of changing, of the five aggregates being independent of any sort of notion of mine and myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: He fully drilled that, to the extent necessary, for the final knowledge, and with that insight, everything was done.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can we say that, basically, the essence, the point is to produce that structure of experience, and then... Understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, like, I mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of unfortunate that this needs to be said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like to be particular, but generally, because, yeah, many people...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you read so much in every sutta, it's just like the final knowledge, the final knowledge, the final understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Putujana can relate to knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just think about the phenomenon of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means when you know something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you must not abandon that notion of knowledge when you're pursuing the way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: As appealing as it is to give in to any personal mechanical technique that sort of numbs you out for a while, makes you very peaceful, it's a very, very dangerous path to take, because you become dependent upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pleasure, that forgetfulness, that oblivion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, initially, everything seems painful, because you want to know everything, but you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's on the basis of that, that you can actually discern important from unimportant, which is an undescription for Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I, what's important knowledge, what it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, but it still is the knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to answer your original question about samatha and vipassana,
[SPEAKER_01]: Vipassana is actively pursuing the discernment of those principles, whatever approach you take, the five aggregates, vipaṁ, upādāna, or peripheral and actual.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything that's based on mindfulness, that's where you cannot have too much of mindfulness, and that's where mindfulness is always first, basically, in whatever list they come up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, vipassana would be actively pursuing the discernment, while samatha would be not actively pursuing the discernment, but maintaining the basis for discernment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, if you maintain the basis for discernment, but not exerting yourself in understanding, you will progress a bit slower in terms of understanding, but nevertheless, you eventually, you start seeing those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know what you're supposed to see, and you keep holding it in front of you, even if you're not necessarily trying to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still hold all the components rightly in front of you,
[SPEAKER_01]: In samatha, that's why samatha carries vipassana.
[SPEAKER_01]: Vice versa, actively pursuing vipassana means you composing that principle and keeping it in front of you, means vipassana is dragging samatha with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not optional, if done rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's like the two yokes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yoke to the two, two, two oxes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one might go slightly forward, another one might... That doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will both be going forward.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you engage in any form of samatha, that is not based on mindfulness, not based on maintaining the same principles, even if you don't necessarily actively pursue them, well, you have no basis for any vipassana, which means that's not samatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's patujana samatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's his premeditation, overmeditation, undermeditation, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that cannot possibly, magically, sort of transfer you into the right, right way of meditating.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just couldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness is in common to vipassana and to samatha.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why every jhāna is done properly, which is what jhāna is when it's done properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has mindfulness as its basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you read one by one sutra, you read other sutras, mindfulness is present in every jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it must be basically founded upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of thinking what kind of contemporary sort of Buddhist schools think and teach, that meditation is some sort of concentration that makes you focus upon something, that you forget everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Think about meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Samādhi literally means composure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're composing something, you need components for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something needs to be composed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something needs to be kept there, composed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the principle, the understanding of mindfulness that we spoke about before.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, think of samādhi or samatha...
[SPEAKER_01]: Think of samādhi or samatha as unwavering mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not actively engaging on the basis of that mindfulness, just being mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mindfulness enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness persisting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like it doesn't change at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Changes while remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because mindfulness is another phenomenon as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindful of experience as a whole, which is the phenomenon that is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it not to be like focused on one particular thing, but just to... Actually, peripheral means
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, basically, from one point of view, you see both ends.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to chase them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to step into the peripheral and forget about actual and chase actual and forget about peripheral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the other one, what was the...
[SPEAKER_01]: That simile... Well, think about the other simile, basically, which can serve the purpose, like a gatekeeper.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't chase people outside of the city, nor inside the city.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just stay at one point from which you know whoever passes here is inside, whoever goes out is outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all you need to know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same sense, that's how you establish your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by chasing the particular sensations or whatever perceptions, but by being mindful of the basis of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they can change as fast as they want.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't lose your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you haven't based your mindfulness on such a fleeting, particular notion, but on a more general, fundamental recognition of the experience as a whole, which is a basis for these things changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't care how they change.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know they'll have to change inside of this city.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they've entered.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: They've ceased.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, they're not my concern.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what about wholesome and unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to get sort of this kind of mindfulness established, developed and established, unwholesome habits, unwholesome behavior, unwholesome engaging with unwholesome need to have been already kept at bay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, sometimes you slip, you engage in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have right mindfulness, it will be quicker for you to kind of readjust, and reset, and start doing things rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the case for an ārya, who can quickly pick back, pick up the training back, and do it even after a slip.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for Pratyūjana, he needs to purify his behavior beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: He needs to have been engaging
[SPEAKER_01]: In a pure behavior, in a sense of not giving in to the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as we spoke a few days ago, that unwholesome, yeah, there is the obvious unwholesome, but often that unwholesome is actually determined by the state of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's rooted in desire,
[SPEAKER_01]: In craving, or if it's not routine desire, in craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what you become aware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, kind of, oh, well, everybody says this is fine, and I'll do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know you'll be doing it for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the reasons of pursuing distraction, carelessness, whatever, and feeling justified about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: That needs to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, these things can take take root, if you obviously apply the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the sūtas say that he practiced restraint by the rules of padamagga.
[SPEAKER_01]: He sees the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, basically, if you recognize the danger in the slightest giving in to the desire, essentially, that you are not following the teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean you don't do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you just do things that are not rooted in your unwholesome desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to go for a walk, because, eh... well, because you're basically feel too lazy to read the suttas, or maybe, although you can, they're right in front of you, you want to go for a walk, and then, that's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is a compromise, you can see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Going for a walk, depending, like, you want to go into the wilderness, well, that's not necessarily... you're not gonna have any kind of sensual distractions there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could sort of do that compromise, because it's quite likely, in the wilderness, your mind will go back to the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, say, you go for a walk and you choose to go to the village.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, well, you will be meeting people, you will be engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might not give rise to any seriously unwholesome desire, or an offense, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, nevertheless, you're going for the purpose of socializing, turning your mind away from the practice, giving in to distraction of others.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: If, for example, you want to go to the wilderness because you want to practice further, then it's same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you go for the same walk, but now it's placed in wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's done for good reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you become responsible for rooting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, like, you live in the monastery, you live in a big temple.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most, like, the temples, they have libraries, Buddhist libraries, every book you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're in your room, bored on the pressure, the dread starts to come up, anxiety, you're a bit tired, you can't keep making the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, well, you know, it's obvious you'll feel too guilty if you just go to the sala or reception room where people are.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, you go to the library to get the book.
[SPEAKER_01]: But deep down, or not even that deep down, just underneath that, you hope that you will meet people in library to get somebody to talk to and get your mind off things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if you say to him, I'm going to the library to take some suttas, nobody will criticize that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everyone will say, yeah, very well, he's really making the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you know that actually you're doing it for completely wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you shouldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there will be a fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sometimes you don't know, actually, because you... Well, you have to know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not necessarily... You don't need a great wisdom of a sotāpanna or an arahant to discern that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to be honest to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why that... the mundane right view is required for any other right view to take place.
[SPEAKER_01]: That recognition, that kind of admitting things to yourself, being transparent to yourself, what is universal, being authentic.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you recognize, why am I going to London?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the main reason?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, like, once you start developing the transparency, that's... that's where the, you know, the contemplation of the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can't help but eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to eat, because otherwise you'll die.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize then, you can eat for unwholesome reasons or you can make the effort and re-root the reasons for your eating that are necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Root them forcefully, if you have to, in wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't give rise to the desire and root them in wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Root them in the purpose of your practice, purpose of this life, purpose of your commitment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to remain healthy, affliction-free, so that you can practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like, oh, eating is bad or eating is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: You make it so.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you remain mindful of the... and if you are mindful of these more general, vague reasons why you eat, like, oh, to become an arahant, and to do this, and to be able to practice, and to be able to apply myself, the desire can't creep in.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you become unmindful, it goes back to the default, which is with the grain, which is with the flood, which is with the desire, with the taste, with the finesse.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same sense, sometimes you might actually have to go to the library.
[SPEAKER_01]: You really want to get these suttas, but you've been carelessly attending to that, unmindfully, and the real reason becomes meeting other people.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you have to re-route it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you have to keep bringing back the other reason for getting the sutta books.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then go to the library, and if you do meet other people, you may therefore end up engaging with them, avoiding them, taking the books, and getting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is this sīla-bhāta-bhāra-matsar?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you fully develop this principle of transparency, paired with the understanding of the basis of mindfulness, that would reveal the sign of the mind, the notion of the phenomenon of the mind, then you will recognize exactly where the purpose of sīla, the virtue, and bhāta, the duties, is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will recognize it, and you wouldn't need to hold on to it, because you took responsibility for the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't recognize it, that's when people say, no, no, no, but it's always good to go and take the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always good to be virtuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it is always good to be virtuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is always good to read the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: But a putujana's mind can make even that unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it doesn't know that, fundamentally, wholesome and unwholesome is rooted in desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, unwholesome is always rooted in desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, in hindsight, you can recognize that, oh yes, of course, sensuality of any kind, anger, ill will of any kind, cruelty of any kind, it's always rooted in desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot reroute the reasons for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you stop doing them beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: You take that on trust, so that you can develop that understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just so that you can blindly adhere to it for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that will not serve as a basis for wisdom and knowledge that we spoke about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, the behavior needs to be purified beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, obviously, the practice of the discernment of the principle, the composure of the principle, and the kind of the knowledge of the principle, eventually, can take the place.